

Rik JG Nuijten PhD

Over 5 years experience in drone-based remote sensing, machine learning and data fusion for the assessment and management of forest ecosystems. Produced related best practices guides and science that continues to be operationalized. Has instructed and created materials for students in post-secondary education related to geospatial data analysis and data science.

Applied Skills

Remote Sensing

Photogrammetric processing, point cloud modelling, multispectral image analysis, drone data

acquisition, field sampling techniques

Data Science

Data visualization, predictive modelling, unsupervised learning, object detection, spatial

pattern analysis, scripting in Python, R & SQL

Soft Skills

Communication

Effective graphic design, reporting, and presentation

Languages

English, Dutch

Methodological Analytical, creative problem-solving, organized

Personal Accountable, adaptable, enthusiastic, reliable, respectful

Social Conflict resolution, inclusive, positive, team-building

Experience

PhD - Remote Sensing in Forestry

May 2019 — June 2024

UBC (Faculty of Forest Resources Management)

Vancouver (CA)

- · Explored the capabilities, limitations, and opportunities of drone-based remote sensing in assessing ecosystem recovery, with a specific focus on digital aerial photogrammetry and vegetation.
- Worked in a top-tier, highly productive lab environment where I collaborated with other students and scientists, participated in various field sampling campaigns, and attended seminars.

Teaching Assistant

June 2019 — November 2022

UBC (Faculty of Forest Resources Management)

Vancouver (CA)

· Developed course materials, supported students with exercises, and facilitated research projects involving geospatial information in the following courses: Data Science in Forest Resources (FRST 505), Geospatial Data Analysis with Python (GEM 530), Observing the Earth from Space (CONS 127), and Project Proposal Development and Proof of Concept (FCOR 599).

Research Intern

September 2018 — March 2019

UBC (Faculty of Forest Resources Management)

Vancouver (CA)

· Investigated the effects of seasonal timing of drone image collection on individual tree detection and mensuration, which was published in a peer-reviewed journal.

Data Analyst

December 2017 — July 2018 Amsterdam (NL)

• Prepared data and analysis for real estate market outlook reports.

GIS Intern

November 2015 — June 2016

De Bilt (NL)

SWECO (Team Geoweb)

CBRE (Team Research)

• Developed Geoweb (Geocortex Essentials) demo applications

Grocery Clerk

December 2010 — October 2015 Bergen op Zoom (NL)

Albert Heijn

Education

MSc - Geographical Information Management and Application (Cum Laude)

September 2016 — December 2018 Utrecht (NL)

Utrecht University (Faculty of Geosciences)

- Investigated the use of drone imagery and object-based image analysis for measuring leafy vegetable crop productivity, which was published in a peer-reviewed journal.
- Took extracurricular courses in Data Management, Python Programming, and Big Data at Wageningen University.

BSc - Human Geography and Spatial Planning

Utrecht (NL)

Utrecht University (Faculty of Geosciences)

September 2013 — July 2016

• Pursued a minor in Geo Information at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam.

Extra Activities

- Bootcamp Instructor at U.S.R. Triton (2016 2017)
- Indoor Cycling Instructor at Newstyle Healthcenters (2017 – 2018)

 Hosted GIS Career Event for GIMA master program (2016 – 2017)

Conferences and Seminar Experience

- Seminar Talk: Surveying keystone plant communities and structures following ecological restoration using drone imagery (9 March 2023, Scion, Rotorua, New Zealand)
- Conference Talk: Mapping vegetation structure, following early regeneration in open boreal forests, using remotely piloted aerial systems (RPAS) based imaging (2 September 2022, ForestSAT, Berlin, Germany)
- Webinar Talk: Monitoring environmental impacts through remote sensing: Innovations and advancements (17 February 2022, Canadian Conservation and Land Management Knowledge Network, online)

Guides and Peer-Reviewed Publications

Chadwick, AJ, TRH Goodbody, CW Bater, LA Martens, RJG Nuijten, S Smith-Tripp, S Grubinger, et al. 2022. "Best Practice Guide to Acquisition of 3D Imagery from (RPAS)." Vancouver, BC, Canada: Department of Forest Resource Management, Faculty of Forestry, University of British Columbia. https://irss-ubc.github.io/GOA_BPG_PUB/.

Nuijten, RJG, NC Coops, TRH Goodbody, and G Pelletier. 2019. "Examining the Multi-Seasonal Consistency of Individual Tree Segmentation on Deciduous Stands Using Digital Aerial Photogrammetry (DAP) and Unmanned Aerial Systems (UAS)." Remote Sensing 11 (7): 739–57.

Nuijten, RJG, NC Coops, CE Prescott, and D Theberge. 2024. "Informing Reclamation Success in Forested Landscapes Using Drone-Based Plant Community Assessments: Enhancing Vegetation Assessments and Reference Site Selection." *Environmental Management* In review.

Nuijten, RJG, NC Coops, D Theberge, and CE Prescott. 2024. "Estimation of Fine-Scale Vegetation Distribution Information from RPAS-Generated Imagery and Structure to Aid Restoration Monitoring." *Science of Remote Sensing* 9: 100114.

Nuijten, RJG, NC Coops, C Watson, and D Theberge. 2021. "Monitoring the Structure of Regenerating Vegetation Using Drone-Based Digital Aerial Photogrammetry." *Remote Sensing* 13 (10): 1942.

Nuijten, RJG, NC Coops, H Zerriffi, and D Theberge. 2024. "Advances in Drone-Based Remote Sensing for Restoration Assessments: Information Uncertainty, Complexity, and Cost-Effectiveness." *Ecosphere* In review.

Nuijten, RJG, L Kooistra, and GB De Deyn. 2019. "Using Unmanned Aerial Systems (UAS) and Object-Based Image Analysis (OBIA) for Measuring Plant-Soil Feedback Effects on Crop Productivity." *Drones* 3 (3): 54.

References

References available upon request.